after reading tons of productivity books
उत्पादकता की ढेरों किताबें पढ़ने के बाद
I came across so many rules like the
मुझे बहुत सारे नियम मिले जैसे
2-year rule the 5 minute rule the 5c
2 साल का नियम, 5 मिनट का नियम, 5c
rule no not that 5-second rule the
नियम नहीं, वह 5 सेकंड का नियम नहीं,
problem is that these rules were meant
समस्या यह है कि ये नियम
for companies or entrepreneurs but I was
कंपनियों या उद्यमियों के लिए थे लेकिन मैं
able to adapt them to my studies during
med school and drastically cut down in
मेडिकल स्कूल के दौरान अपनी पढ़ाई में इन्हें अपनाने में सक्षम था और अपने विलंब में भारी कटौती की,
my procrastination so I'm going to share
इसलिए मैं
with you two different two-minute rules
आपके साथ अगले 2 मिनट के लिए दो अलग-अलग दो मिनट के नियम साझा करने जा रहा हूं,
for the next 2 minutes the first 2
पहला 2
minute rule comes from getting things
मिनट का नियम
done by David Allen he says if it takes
डेविड एलन द्वारा चीजों को पूरा करने से आता है, उनका कहना है कि अगर किसी काम को करने में
2 minutes to do get it done right now
for example if I need to take out the
trash today it takes 2 minutes to do so
2 मिनट लगते हैं तो उसे अभी कर लें, उदाहरण के लिए अगर मुझे आज कचरा बाहर
if I'm thinking about it now might as
well just do it now instead of writing
it down on a to-do list or probably
forgetting about it or having to come
निकालने की जरूरत है तो इसमें 2 मिनट लगते हैं, अगर मैं इसके बारे में अभी सोच रहा हूं तो इसे टू-डू सूची में लिखने या शायद इसे भूल जाने या
back to it later which takes more than 2
बाद में वापस आने के बजाय इसे अभी कर लेना बेहतर होगा, जिसमें 2 मिनट से अधिक समय लगता है,
minutes that's how I see it so here's a
मैं इसे इसी तरह देखता हूं, इसलिए
list of things that might take 2 minutes
throughout the day like organizing your
desk or Watering your plants or clipping
those nasty Nails I just do it when I
notice it but these little things start
ये छोटी-छोटी चीजें
to add up so this rule biases my brain
जुड़ने लगती हैं इसलिए यह नियम मेरे मस्तिष्क को
towards taking action and away from
कार्रवाई करने और टालमटोल से दूर रखता है।
procrastination the second two-minute
दूसरा दो मिनट का
rule comes from Atomic Habits by James
नियम जेम्स क्लियर की एटॉमिक हैबिट्स से आता है।
Clear he says when you're trying to do
वह कहते हैं कि जब आप
something you don't really want to do
कुछ ऐसा करने की कोशिश कर रहे होते हैं जो आप वास्तव में नहीं करना चाहते हैं तो
simplify the test down to 2 minutes or
परीक्षण को 2 मिनट या उससे कम समय तक सरल बना दें,
less so doing your entire reading
इसलिए आपका संपूर्ण पढ़ने का
assignment becomes just reading one
काम सिर्फ एक
paragraph or memorizing the entire
पैराग्राफ पढ़ने या संपूर्ण
periodic table becomes memorizing just
आवर्त सारणी को याद करने में बदलकर सिर्फ
10 flash cards now some of you might
10 फ्लैश कार्ड याद करने बन जाता है। अब आप में से कुछ
think yeah this is just a Jedi mind
सोच सकते हैं कि हाँ यह सिर्फ जेडी माइंड
trick like why would I fall for it how
ट्रिक है, जैसे मैं इसके लिए क्यों गिरूँगा,
is this at all sustainable and to that
यह कैसे टिकाऊ है और इसके लिए
he says when you're starting out limit
वह कहते हैं कि जब आप शुरू कर रहे हैं तो
yourself to only only 2 minutes so back
अपने आप को केवल 2 मिनट तक सीमित रखें, इसलिए
in med school I wanted to build a habit
मेड स्कूल में मैं
of studying for 1 hour every day before
dinner so I tried this trick but I
रात के खाने से पहले हर दिन 1 घंटे पढ़ाई करने की आदत बनाना चाहता था, इसलिए मैंने यह तरकीब आजमाई
limited myself to Just 2 minutes I'd sit
down open my laptop study for 2 minutes
and then Clos my laptop and went to do
something else it seems unproductive at
first right it seems stupid but staying
लेकिन मैंने खुद को सिर्फ
consistent with this two-minute routine
2 मिनट तक सीमित रखा, मैं अपने लैपटॉप को खोलकर 2 मिनट तक
day after day meant that I was becoming
the type of person who studies daily I
पढ़ाई करता और फिर अपना लैपटॉप बंद कर देता और कुछ और करने
was mastering the habit of just showing
बस दिखने की आदत
up because a habit needs to be
क्योंकि एक आदत को
established before it can be expanded
स्थापित करने से पहले इसे विस्तारित किया जा सकता है
upon if I can't become a person who
अगर मैं एक ऐसा व्यक्ति नहीं बन सकता जो
studies for Just 2 minutes a day I'd
दिन में सिर्फ 2 मिनट पढ़ता है तो मैं कभी भी ऐसा
never be able to become the person that
व्यक्ति नहीं बन पाऊंगा जो
studies for an hour a day you got to
दिन में एक घंटा पढ़ता है आपको
start somewhere but starting small is
कहीं से तो शुरुआत करनी होगी लेकिन छोटी शुरुआत करना
easier there's a lot of other useful
आसान है किताबों में कई अन्य उपयोगी
tips from books I cover more here in
टिप्स हैं मैंने यहां
this video on three books in 3 minutes
3 मिनट में तीन पुस्तकों पर इस वीडियो में अधिक बताया है
check it out and if you guys like these
इसे देखें और अगर आप लोगों को इस
types of videos let me know in the
प्रकार के वीडियो पसंद आते हैं तो मुझे
comments below I'll see you there bye
नीचे टिप्पणियों में बताएं मैं वहां आपसे मिलूंगा अलविदा